Chapter 128.
The Peekquad meets the Rachel.
Next day a large ship, the Rachel, was described, bearing directly down upon
the Peekquad, all her spars thickly clustering with men. At the time the
Peekquad was making good speed through the water, but as the broad-winged
windward stranger shot nigh to her, the boastful sails all fell together as
blank bladders that are burst, and all life fled from the smitten hull.
Bad news, she brings bad news, muttered the old mansman. But heir, her
commander, who with trumpet to mouth, stood up in his boat, air he could
hopefully hail, Ahab's voice was heard.
Has seen the white whale?
I yesterday have you seen a whaleboat a drift? Throttling his joy, Ahab
negatively answered this unexpected question, and would have fain boarded
the stranger when the stranger captain himself, having stopped his vessel's
way, was seen descending her side. A few keen pulls in his boat hook soon
clenched the Peekquad's main chains, and he sprang to the deck. Immediately he
was recognized by Ahab for a Nantucketer he knew, but no formal salutation was exchanged.
Where was he? Not killed. Not killed, cried Ahab, closely advancing. How was
it? It seemed that somewhere late in the afternoon of the day previous, while
three of the strangers boats were engaged with a shaw of whales, which had
led them some four or five miles from the ship, and while they were yet in
swift chase to Windward, the white hump and head of Moby Dick, had suddenly
loomed up out of the water, not very far to lure, whereupon the fourth rigged
boat, a reserved one, had been instantly lowered in chase, after a keen sail
before the wind, This fourth boat, the swiftest keeled of all, seemed to have
succeeded in fastening, at least as well as the man at the mast head could tell
anything about it. In the distance he saw the diminished dotted boat, and then
a swift gleam of bubbling white water, and after that nothing more, whence it
was concluded that the stricken whale must have indefinitely run away with his
pursuers, as often happens. There was some apprehension, but no positive alarm
as yet. The recall signals were placed in the riggings. darkness came on and
forced to pick up her three far to windward boats, air going in quest of
the fourth one in the precisely opposite direction, the ship had not only been
necessitated to leave that boat to its fate till near midnight, but for the
time to increase her distance from it, but the rest of her crew being at last
safe aboard, she crowded all sail stencil on stencil after the missing
boat, kindling a fire in her tripods for a beacon, and every other man a loft on
the lookout. But though, when she had thus sailed a sufficient distance to
gain the presumed place of the absent ones when last seen, though she then
paused to lower her spare boats to pull all around her, and not finding
anything, had again dashed on, again, paused and lowered her boats, and though
she had thus continued doing till daylight, yet not the least glimpse of
the missing keel had been seen.
The story told, "The stranger captain immediately went on to reveal his object
in boarding the Peekquad. He desired that ship to unite with his own in the
search, by sailing over the sea, some four or five mi apart on parallel lines,
and so sweeping a double horizon, as it were." "I will wager something now,"
whispered Stub to Flask, "that someone in that missing boat wore off that
captain's best coat. Mayhap his watch.
He's so cursed, anxious to get it back.
Who ever heard of two pious whale ships cruising after one missing whaleboat in
the height of the whailing season? See, Flask, only see how pale he looks, pale
in the very buttons of his eyes. Look, it wasn't the coat. It must have been
the my boy. My own boy is among them.
For God's sake, I beg. I conjure. Here exclaimed the stranger captain to Ahab,
who thus far had but isoly received his petition. For 8 and 40 hours, let me
charter your ship. I will gladly pay for it, and roundly pay for it, if there be
no other way. For 8 and 40 hours only, only that you must. Oh, you must, and
you shall do this thing.
His son, cried Stub. Oh, it's his son.
He's lost. I take back the coat in the watch. What says Ahab? We must save that boy.
He's drowned with the rest of them last night, said the old man sailor standing
behind them. I heard all of you heard their spirits.
Now, as it shortly turned out, what made this incident of the Rachel's the more
melancholy was the circumstance that not only was one of the captain's sons among
the number of the missing boats crew, but among the number of the other boats
crews, and at the same time, but on the other hand, separated from the ship
during the dark vicissitudes of the chase, there had been still another son,
and that for a time the wretched father was plunged to the bottom of the crulest
perplexity, which was only solved for him by his chief mates instinctively
adopting the ordinary procedure of a whale ship in such emergencies, that is,
when placed between jeopardized but divided boats, always to pick up the
majority first. But the captain, for some unknown constitutional reason, had
refrained from mentioning all this, and not till forced to it by Ahab's iciness,
did he allude to his one yet missing boy, a little lad, but 12 years old,
whose father, with the earnest but unmisgiving hardyhood of a nantucker's
paternal love, had thus early sought to initiate him in the perils and wonders
of a vocation almost immemorialally the destiny of all his race. Nor does it
unfrequently occur that Nantucket captains will send a son of such tender
age away from them for a protracted three or four years voyage in some other
ship than their own, so that their first knowledge of a whaleman's career shall
be unenervated by any chance display of a father's natural but untimely
partiality or undue apprehensiveness and concern.
Meanwhile, now the stranger was still beseeching his poor boon of Ahab, and
Ahab still stood like an anvil, receiving every shock, but without the
least quivering of his own. I will not go, said the stranger, till you say I to
me. Do me as you would have me do to you
in the like case, for you too have a boy, Captain Ahab, though but a child
and nestling safely at home now. A child of your old age, too. Yes, yes, you
relent. I see it. Run, run, men, now and stand by to square in the yards. A vast,
cried Ahab. Touch not a rope yarn.
Then in a voice that prolongingly molded every word, "Captain gardener,
I will not do it. Even now I lose time.
Goodbye. Goodbye. God bless you, man.
And may I forgive myself, but I must go.
Mr. Starbucks, look at the binnacle watch, and in 3 minutes from this
present instant, warn off all strangers.
Then brace forward again and let the ship sail as before.
Hurriedly turning with averted face, he descended into his cabin, leaving the
strange captain transfixed at this unconditional and utter rejection of his
so earnest suit. But starting from his enchantment, Gardener silently hurried
to the side, more fell than stepped into his boat, and returned to his ship.
Soon the two ships diverged their wakes, and long as the strange vessel was in
view, she was seen to yaw hither and thither at every dark spot, however
small, on the sea. This way, and that, her yards were swung round, starboard,
and larbor she continued to tack. Now she beat against a head sea, and again
it pushed her before it, while all the while her mass and yards were thickly
clustered with men as three tall cherry trees when the boys are cherrying among
the boughs. But by her still halting course and winding woeful way, you
plainly saw that this ship that so wept with spray still remained without
comfort. She was Rachel weeping for her children because they were not.